Finding Aid for Geraldine Brasie photograph collection
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Geraldine Brasie photograph collection
1924-1934
Brasie, Geraldine.
2014110 Aa 2
Detroit, Mich. resident and world traveler, who journeyed widely throughout Europe and Asia in the first half of the 20th century. Collection primarily consists of photographic prints and negatives documenting Brasie's travels to countries around the world.
3.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Donald Brasie (Donor no. 9526 ) in August 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Geraldine Brasie was born in Detroit, Mich. in 1899. After graduating from Detroit's Central High School, she earned her B.A. and M.S. degrees from the University of Michigan. Prior to completing her M.S. degree, she spent a year conducting research at the Pasteur Institute in Paris. In 1923, she became a chemistry teacher at Northwestern High School. Brasie was granted travel leave in 1930, embarking on adventures throughout the globe. Her travels took her to places such as the British Isles, Europe, India, Tibet, China, and Japan, just to name a few. An avid photographer, Brasie took photographs of people and places throughout her travels, developing her film upon returning home and making slides for use in travelogue presentations she gave.
In 1934, she returned to teaching in Detroit, where she joined the social studies faculty at Mackenzie High School, teaching there until her retirement in 1963. Brasie passed away in 1976.
Housed at the front of the collection are a few Manuscript Materials folders containing biographical information on Brasie, information on the photographs in the collection, a 1931 letter describing a visit to the Church of the Holy Sepulcher in Jerusalem, and postcards.
The Photographic Materials comprise the bulk of the collection. It consists of prints and negatives and is arranged primarily by country. Occasionally, a country name may be used as it was at the time of Brasie's travels and differently from current use. For instance, photographs taken in what is today Pakistan are filed under India and photographs from what is now Israel are filed under Palestine. Photographs whose location is unidentified have been filed under Miscellaneous. Images depict historic sites, daily activities of people, street scenes in towns and in the countryside. Brasie also took photographs of her friends and their families, particularly those living in Japan.
Subjects:
Brasie, Geraldine.; Voyages and travels.; Women travelers--20th century.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Country life--China.; Country life--India.; City & town life--Asia.; City & town life--Europe.; City & town life--Japan.
Genre Terms:
Black-and-white negatives.; Photographs.
- Manuscript materials
  - Biographical, undated (Box 1)
  - Letter, 1931 (Box 1)
    (visiting the Church of the Holy Sepulchre in Jerusalem)
  - Photographic information, undated (Box 1)
  - Postcards, 1927-1934 (Box 1)
- Photographic materials
  - Prints
    - Bhutan/Tibet/India, circa 1932 (Box 1)
    - Brazil, undated (Box 1)
    - Burma, 1933 (Box 1)
    - Cambodia/Thailand-Angkor Wat, Bangkok, 1933 (Box 1)
    - China
      - General, 1933; 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Yangtze River, 1933 (Box 1)
    - Dutch East Indies, circa 1933 (Box 1)
    - Egypt, 1931 (Box 1)
    - England
      - 1926 (Box 1)
      - 1930 (Box 1)
      - undated (Box 1)
    - France, 1924 (Box 1)
    - France/Holland/Italy/Switzerland/Unidentified, circa 1924-1926; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - France/Switzer, 1924 (Box 1)
    - Germany
      - 1926 (Box 1)
      - 1931 (Box 1)
    - Germany (Rothenburg)/Hol, circa 1926 (Box 1)
    - Greece, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Greece to Syria, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Hol, 1926 (Box 2)
    - India
      - General, 1931-1933; 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Ahmednagar, Rahuri, Ellora, Ajanta, Bombay, circa 1931 (Box 2)
      - Blood Sacrifice, early 1930s (Box 2)
      - Bombay, 1931 (Box 2)
      - Calcutta, Udaipur, early 1930s (Box 2)
      - Delhi, Lehore, Kashmir, Khyber, Sind, Mt. Ahee, 1932 (Box 2)
      - Kalimpong, early 1930s (Box 2)
      - Kashmir/Khyber Pass, 1932 (Box 2)
      - Southern, early 1930s (Box 2)
      - Udaipur, Jaipur, Agra, Delhi, early 1930s (Box 2)
    - India/Burma/Thai, 1933 (Box 2)
    - India/Dutch East Indies/Ceylon, 1931-1933 (Box 2)
    - India/Tibet, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Ire, 1930 (Box 2)
    - Italy, undated (Box 2)
    - Japan
      - General, 1933; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - American Families, 1933; 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Hokkaido, 1933 (Box 3)
      - Journey to, 1933 (Box 3)
      - Sendai, Kyoto, 1933 (Box 3)
    - Mexico, undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Nepal, 1932 (Box 3)
    - Nepal/Mongolia?, undated (Box 3)
    - Palestine, 1931 (Box 3)
    - Philippines, early 1930s (Box 3)
    - Saudi Arabia (Jedda) and Ship, 1931 (Box 3)
    - Scot, 1930 (Box 3)
    - Spain
      - 1926 (Box 3)
      - 1930 (Box 3)
    - Syria, 1931 (Box 3)
    - Syria/Palestine, 1931 (Box 4)
    - Syria/Turkey, 1931 (Box 4)
    - Thai, 1933 (Box 4)
      (May contain photographs from other areas)
    - Tibet, 1932 (Box 4)
  - Negatives
    - Cambodia/Thailand/Singapore-Angkor Wat, Bangkok, Singapore, 1933 (Box 4)
    - Egypt, 1931 (Box 4)
    - Egypt/Spain, circa 1931 (Box 4)
    - Germany-Black Forest (Negatives), circa 1926 (Box 4)
    - Germany (Rothenburg)/Switzer, circa 1926 (Box 4)
    - India-Kalimpong, early 1930s (Box 4)
    - India/Ceylon, early 1930s; 3 folders (Box 4)
      (May contain negatives from other areas)
    - Japan, 1933 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4)
    - Nepal/Tibet?, circa 1932 (Box 4)